now I don't know about you but uh these
days I'm using AI in my everyday life
quite a lot like to help me create art
write code write formal letters ask
questions brainstorm all kinds of stuff
and you know that's only really been
possible very
recently uh I think AI researchers we're
pretty privileged to be in this time in
human history and and see these
improvements happening in real time um
but and we've seen how quickly they
evolve but I still think there's a lot
left to do um I think we can
expect still more large improvements
even in you know the near future in next
few few years and we've seen that even
in the the last months right with 01 R1
and so on uh big improvements uh in
various benchmarks in reasoning um and
after all that you know it's a very
young field overall but like you know
that that sub field uh with learning
Chain of Thought I mean Chain of Thought
itself is only really from
2022 so uh yeah I think it's it's really
impressive how how fast things are
moving um
so in the context of this talk I'm going
to be talking about uh methods for
self-improving uh self-improving
language models and that means getting
better
at tasks in particular that will mean
that they're getting better at reasoning
so that they can better get better at
those tasks uh so uh for an AI to train
itself I that means it needs to do this
introspection as it's training so uh you
know normal sort of classical training
was like this fixed data set and it
would sort of learned from it but that's
kind of moving now a little bit where
you know in like reinforcement learning
setups uh and particularly with
reinforcement learning from AI feedback
uh models are sort of like training
themselves in a much more sophisticated
way for example we can imagine models
that create new challenges tasks that
train themselves on they can evaluate
themselves whether they're getting them
right so we call that self-rewarding and
then update themselves based on what
they've understood so that means then
they're going to
be getting more knowledge more reasoning
ability and so research question is can
they do this kind of training on
themselves uh and can that help them
become superhuman uh so I have a picture
down here of one particular approach uh
for that that's called self-rewarding
language models which I'm going to be
talking about a bit later um uh but in
terms of reasoning when we're doing this
kind of
self-improving you can look at this as
like two different ways of of improving
reasoning
so uh these are called system one and
system two sometimes by people so system
one uh like in humans we we would see
that as reactive and relies on
associations and in in machine learning
models or llms it can be the same thing
so you can re you can think of the
Transformer itself like the the neural
network as this kind of Performing this
system one reasoning so where you're you
have these uh hidden states in the
neural network is going through a whole
bunch of
multiplications uh attentions and so on
uh that could be seen as your system one
reasoning so in that case you have a
fixed compute per token you're directly
outputting the answer uh but there's
some problems with
llms uh as we have them now in
particular they can learn spirous
unwanted uh correlations there's
hallucination sick off fency
jailbreaking and I'm going to I'm going
to show some of those things later and
then you can try and fix this stuff with
what's called system two so that's more
deliberate and effortful thinking and
the most uh common way we think of that
system to uh today is by generating like
language tokens that are a Chain of
Thought So now that's not just you know
the the pushing these numbers through
the neuronet you're actually looking at
the tokens the neuronet outputs as as a
thought stream before the final tokens
it will be um the final response now
What's um powerful when you do that is
that that system to Chain of Thought
reasoning can actually do a whole bunch
of um stuff like planning uh search
verification various kinds of reasoning
even though it's generating sort of um
Auto regressively you know left to right
uh it could still potentially do all
that
kind of uh sets of thoughts as you'll
see models like deep SE 0103 can
do so uh yeah so those are the two kinds
of things that we can effectively
improve then try and improve like the
the architecture or the weights of the
model and improve system one or try and
improve how it generates these chains of
thought or other ways of doing system to
before it outputs a response I mean
obviously they're related because it's
the same language model doing both
things but um so that's that's the goal
try and try and do this uh self-learning
to improve these things first um I'm
going to go through some uh history of
how we got where we are like today and
and then talk about you know more uh
recent recent works from the last year
or so after I go through this history
but before we're going to start uh
pre-2020 to prehistory if you like so
language modeling itself um that goes
way back I mean yeah Claude Shannon in
uh 1950s talked about that um so it's
about taking language and predicting the
next to token or next word each step and
obviously that's the uh pre-training
mechanism we use for large language
models and that's how they get their
name uh where you're just trying to
predict the probability of these tokens
we do this now on this massive corpora
and um pick up those probability
distributions
um so in
2003 there's sort of one of the first
methods for doing that with a a neuron
Network um that's Benjo Dam and vanon so
they had um word embeddings at the first
layer and then you know various various
layers 10 soft Max to get get the final
prediction and uh I just put an
interesting quote
there in their conclusions that they
they say there's probably a lot more to
be done to improve the model the
architecture computational efficiency
and they'd like to increase the capacity
without increasing training time because
they want to deal with corpor of
hundreds of millions of words so you
know that's kind of where we got to uh
some years later um now that was 2003
most of the 2000s actually uh the
research wasn't really focused on neural
networks it was focused on support
victim machines so you know these kernel
classifiers um I worked in that area too
as you can see there's a paper from me
um and you know it was kind of that well
held back to the llm story at least for
a few years so here I have a a slide for
myself
Ral Kar from 2008 presented icml where
we were trying to argue that the support
Vector Machines of the day they were
used in these Cascades of systems parts
of speech taggers and name dentity
recognizers and paes and it's not a good
idea because we could train the whole
thing end to end with a neural network
um and you know no one was will you
doing that then um so we had a paper at
that time um um unified architecture for
NLP which we consider sort of the
successor to the Benjo work from 2003
there um so here what we did was we also
had a neuron network with um uh word
embeddings at the first layer then
convolutional layers uh Max over time
which is a kind of Proto attention and
uh followed by a softmax and we showed
that you could train the train this
model as a sort of mass language model
on something like
Wikipedia which actually was pretty
tricky at the time with the computer we
had and it could learn some pretty
interesting things like you could see
from the word similarities this is
obviously prew word ofc which I think
was 2013 uh which is a simpler model
right this is a more complex neuronet um
that you could do that so you could
pre-rain on Wikipedia and then
afterwards you could fine tune on tasks
of interests like part speech tagging
name density chunking
srl and that worked um so yeah this was
kind
of this was a uh a predecessor to where
we are today as well um it was
interesting because at the time uh that
wasn't appreciated by everyone in the
NLP community so the in the Stanford
natural language group they had a um
reading group there where they called it
a SML paper that was kind of on
their on their public website um and
then this same paper won test of time
award at icml
2018 um and then you know Stanford
University uh then opened the center for
research on Foundation models and their
um position paper called that same paper
president work so we kind of went from
to president in in that number
of years and that's kind of how uh the
field changed of course
um you know these papers I've talked
about just a few papers there's many
many papers right they all uh build on
each other um I don't like to think of
you know kind of like uh one paper that
was the paper that that did something
because uh you know they're they're all
um all this work you know Builds on top
of um of the brilliant work before but
uh so I just show a few here of a
timeline though um of how these things
went um and uh yeah the interesting
thing is of how fast the um use of
neuronet in um NLP um and machine
learning grew um uh from this from this
time from say 2008 to 2018 so there was
like four papers in icml 2008 with
the words deep or neuro in them and and
I'm sort of co-author on two of them and
then there's like 100 in icml 2018
obviously uh this is a neuronetwork
based things are are the majority today
um that's the Paradigm of today of
course can't say what's going to be in
the future but uh it's looking like a
pretty powerful approach
um yeah so of course we were interested
in pushing this F further and you know
making these models reason so uh in uh
2015 we devised this set of tasks very
simple task called the baby tasks
uh which yeah ask these simple questions
given little stories um but the neuronet
of the day um lstms actually couldn't
solve them um and so we were hoping that
they could sort of spark innovation of
new methods
around the same time the uh llm
attention mechanism was born in 2014 so
the bonoo Benjo paper so that was a
um built for machine translation where
uh the sort you'd have a tension between
uh the target sentence words and the
source sentence words so that you could
have an alignment between the words in
the in the two languages so you could
translate them you can see this this uh
sort of uh attention map picture in the
middle of the slide here
so yeah what we showed was that uh for
these kind of baby reasoning tasks uh if
we stack these layers of
attention um then you could actually do
multiple reasoning steps so if you've
got a
question like uh where is uh John here
so Daniel went to the bathroom Mary
traveled to the hallway John went to the
bedroom John traveled to the bathroom
where Mary went to the office where is
John um then you could attend to these
uh correct sentences to get that right
actually that one's pretty easy because
you only need to attend to John travel
to the bathroom the last sentence but
then that's called one one supporting
fact uh question but then you have a two
supporting fact question where it's a
little trickier so there uh John dropped
the milk John took the milk there Sandra
went back to the bathroom John moved to
the hallway Mary went back to the
bedroom and the question is where is the
milk so now you have to see that uh the
model will attend on like the first two
layers uh you can see the attention
scores here in hop one hop two hop three
uh this is in the story two two
supporting facts you see it attends to
the sentence John took the milk there
and so now it it knows that John has the
milk and then it can attend to this next
sentence John moved to the hallway in
the further layers of the neuron Network
so that it can answer the hallway is the
correct answer so this was basically
showing how in these very simple
problems uh the tension mechanism when
stacked layer by layer can give you more
sophisticated reasoning and so this was
uh built into this neuron network of the
time called a memory Network so it had
these stuck layers of attention query
and key embeddings position embeddings
so it knew which sentence or token uh
was being attended to neural networks
between tension layers and a final
softmax layer and so in many ways you
know it was a kind of a predecessor to
the Transformer which improved on this
recipe with some other things like
multi-head attention self attention and
normalization and yeah that led us to
2017 um W with the Advent of the
Transformer and that's kind of more or
less the architecture we're using today
with some tweaks and then Bert in 2018
showed that you know a mass language
model with a
Transformer uh could work very well
um and uh yeah I just wanted to link
that to a paper from
2014 the um with sit Vinos and
quar uh which was um showing that uh you
could do sequence to sequence learning
with networks now I think you know that
that wasn't with
attention uh uh with attention Maps yet
but still uh the conclusions from that
paper were were uh essentially the
scaling hypothesis that we we're using
today so you can see this conclusion
slide if you have a large big data set
and you train a very big neuron Network
then success is guaranteed it's a little
bit glib but um yeah this scaling
hypothesis essentially when ilasa went
to open AI uh they drove this hypothesis
uh you know um making gpt2 GPT 1 2 3 4
and so on right these uh bigger models
more data and indeed this this has
worked so these are basically the
ingredients that have taken us to some
degree sort of llms everywhere so I
asked actually an llm to give me a list
of of llms that have come out in year
orders this doesn't include all of them
but you can see
see a bunch uh that have come out
here
um uh but you know that's just so far
been about um mostly about language
modeling the language model objective
function and that isn't actually enough
so we do need other ways of training
these models and I would characterize
sort of 2020 onwards as um exploring
that more deeply now we have these
better language models
um so uh 2019 actually we did a work on
uh dialogue agents which we call the
self-feeding chatbot where they could
train not only just with this sort of
language model objective but by um using
a reward model so we train a reward
model and then during conversations with
humans uh if it thinks there's a um a
large reward for one of the things it
said it can add that back into the
training set and then uh do supervised
fine tuning on this uh everg growing
data set so this was kind of a pretty
simple version of um what's being done
today uh with um sort of yeah RL uh HF
and RL aif um then in uh 2020 uh we
released this uh blender bot model that
was
a a pre pre-trained language model up to
about 10 billion parameters and then
crucially uh we don't just use the
language model uh pre-training objective
we supervise fine tune that on dialogue
data which was human
annotated and um then uh when you uh
used um you evaluated this with humans
they actually said our best models were
about as engaging as the average human
and Superior to another model uh from
Google called Mina at the time
um but the actual recipes that we use
today we do use supervis fine tuning
today but you know there's some more
sophisticated stuff as well right so in
2022 you had the instruct GPT uh paper
um which uh advocate ated more for
reinforcement learning from Human
feedback so what you do there is you um
have this sort of sft stage where you
collect demonstration data uh from
humans that's step one but step two you
also collect comparison data so which of
these two responses is better A or B and
then get humans to rank those and then
you train a reward model so similar to
how we had a reward model in the
self-feeding chatbot but then uh you use
uh reinforcement learning with that
reward model to then kind of generalize
those um comparisons with the reward
model function to uh to new generations
from your policy and uh try and make
your model better by
generating responses and essentially
judging with this raw model and fixing
itself right so that's kind of um more
of a step towards uh this
self-training uh kind of goal beyond the
language model uh training
Criterion um and then there's sort of an
alternative to rlf well it's uh a little
bit simpler called direct preference
optimization I mentioned because it's
also pretty popular uh DPO uh so it sort
of says okay let's not use a reward
model if we've got preference data we're
just going to directly
uh push the probability of the chosen in
a preference pair sort of up and the
probability of the of the rejecting the
preference pair so these would be two
possible outputs from the model push one
up push one down so there's a sort of a
margin between the two um and uh you
know in certain experiments DPO Works
quite well compared
to PO rhf um and then sft can work but
generally a little worse but it depends
kind of on the setting and um I think I
think in some cases you really do need
the the full reinforcement learning um
because your uh policy is going to
change right um so the DPO just with a
fixed preference data like that can't
take that into account um but we'll see
uh ways of uh fixing that by making it
iterative as well
uh but overall you choose one of those
methods sft rhf or DPO and uh you know F
fine-tune your language model with one
of them and then you get pretty good
instruction following so there isn't
necessarily sort of this explicit Chain
of Thought reasoning yet but uh compared
to the um original language models
you're doing really well so for example
here this is from the instruct GPT paper
you've got this prompt what's the
purpose of of this uh this code
gpt3 without the sort of fine-tuning
doesn't do a very good job but instruct
GPT does a much better job on the right
hand side so obviously yeah today we all
know quite a lot about using these chat
GPT type models as we're mostly yeah a
lot of the population is using them at
this this
stage so okay that got me up to um
up to basically having a really good
system one model right it takes in this
input say this instruction it directly
spits out an output but it isn't doing
the system to reasoning
so that's kind of the next
step and um yeah between say 2022 and
2023 the approach to doing that was what
I would call a prompting approach uh and
so of I'm going to talk about those
first and then we're going to look at um
more modern things from the last year or
so where where we're going to more
trained directly to to do this system to
reasoning
instead so Chain of Thought prompting uh
the uh initial papers they did that in a
couple of ways one was by uh what's
called fuse shot prompting you would
have say for some maths task you would
have examples of the kind of Chain of
Thought reasoning you would like to see
so say uh if you had unn eight
shot uh examples you'd have eight
examples of doing uh reasoning so it can
be that's shown here with the instead of
just saying the answer is 11 as in the
um in standard prompting you would have
Roger started with five balls two kinds
of three tennis balls each is six tennis
balls 5 plus 6 = 11 the answer is 11
right so that's the Chain of Thought
there um that's highlighted so you'd
have examples of that in the prompt and
now you would um generate from the
language model and it's going to um
mimic that F shop prompting and use
Chain of Thought and so that was kind of
uh one of the first approaches of
prompting and then uh in the other paper
here language large language models are
zero shot reasoners they showed actually
you can be even simpler you could just
say let's think step by step in the
prompt and that could still uh bring
about the steps these chains of thought
could happen that it could generate
before it generates a final
response and uh you get really big
improvements on on math tasks so you
know you could go from say 10% on gsm AK
up to uh 40 or
50% um so yeah uh that's kind of really
spurred people to uh push the system two
approaches further and you know it's not
just math tasks that that works
for so you know you can also look at the
other failures of system one of the the
base language model it also has a
factuality and hallucination issues
right so here's an example query name
some politicians who born in New York
and the the third one it lists here
think this is from chat GPT is Michael
Bloomberg which is
incorrect um so you can try and set up a
a system to reasoning type Chain of
Thought to fix this problem so it's not
a math problem right so that's a paper
we did called chain of
verification where the idea is you get
this first Baseline response you can
think of that now as your dve draft so
it's not actually your final response
it's part of your chain of thought and
then given that draft you uh the
language model asks itself more
questions to sort of check its own draft
so it could ask you know where was
Hillary Clinton born where was Donald
Trump born where was Michael Bloomberg
born and then answer those again as
single questions now the answer might be
different than uh sort of writing out
this whole uh list from the names on
politicians question because it's sort
of phrased differently you actually get
a different response from the model and
models tend to be better actually at
these single um question answer pairs
that are short compared to these long
kind of responses they write they
they're more likely to get something
wrong somewhere in the long response so
when you plan those verifications of
those verification questions and execute
them you can actually get the model to
see its own discrepancy so now it
actually knows that Michael Bloomberg
was born in Boston even though it's
included him in the list of politicians
who are who are born in New York and now
you can make it kind of uh cross check
itself and see that it was it was wrong
and write a final uh verified response
and treat the old one as a draft and and
now it gets that correct so that's
that's kind of uh you know a somewhat
different
um Chain of Thought system to reasoning
compared to the math problems and uh
yeah in that in that work we showed that
on uh various knowledge tasks you can
get large performance in Precision like
three times as good uh with that
approach
so yeah I would and um you know you
could think oh that sort of uh maybe
because that paper was from a little
while ago um that you know it might be
fixed today but actually I I tried on
chat GPT for o and it's still making
these kind of mistakes like here I did a
query list 30 most famous women Ai and
it included yosu Benji in the list or
what prominent women work at open Ai and
it said ilas said skver and
uh as the first in the list so um you
know still still something definitely
needs to be fixed and you can fix it
with this sort of system to reasoning I
think actually uh 01 does does better
but um
yeah
um yeah and there's other things you can
do with this system to reasoning as well
uh so here's another problem with
language models um that they have
what's called uh semantic leakage and
copeny so when you do attention uh
because it's a soft attention it's not
um sharp you you know you're assigning
probabilities across um the context so
there'll be all these sort of nonzero um
values and it means the whole context
can affect the llm output and this can
be this can be bad because uh you know
even basically we see irrelevant Parts
which look sort of superficially
correlated tend to have an effect so for
example a prompt like he likes ants his
favorite food is can get completed by
the language model was ant covered
chocolate which you know isn't
particularly desirable he likes yellow
he works as a school bus driver um
that's from
Gel um in
24 um
sort of I see this as a similar problem
the siany problem if you say something
like as an instruction I think that the
sun is yellow when viewed from space
what do you think so you kind of Prime
with the the wrong
answer because actually that's an
illusion caused by atmosphere um then it
will actually agree the llm tends to
agree with you uh and say yes the sun is
actually yellow when viewed from space
so I sort of see that as a similar
problem that basically you've got that
that text in the context and it tends to
attend to it and uh and get things wrong
it's another example if you add some
facts about some City in the context
like Sunny Veil and then you ask for
someone's birthplace it's likely to say
Sunny Veil is the answer um yeah I just
typed in this one uh today did open AI
have a model called self Fe feeding at
one time and it checked you 40 replied
yes open AI introduced the concepts of
self-feeding in the self-feeding chatbot
paper which you know that wasn't
actually from open AI that was from
Facebook AI research so again you can
you can still Prime these you know this
is a sort of current day problem um so
how can you fix that with system to
reasoning so there was a paper call
system to attention we did uh last
uh that was uh yeah 20 end of 2023 I
think um where you do this Chain of
Thought reasoning which attempts to
rewrite the original instruction and
remove the bias so again this is done by
prompting so essentially The Prompt is
to give the original instruction and
then ask the language model rewrite this
instruction remove the irrelevant parts
and the bias and then you'll get a new
instruction and then you get the
language model to answer the Rewritten
instruction right so you want get rid of
this bias and then you can get um you
can get better results you're not biased
as much by this issue so for example the
I think the sun is yellow when viewed
from space what do you think when you
use this um sort of Chain of Thought
system to attention to rewrite that it
would rewrite it as I'm curious about
the color of the sun view from space can
you provide information on this topic so
it's remove the yellow which was kind of
you know um biasing the question to a
certain
answer and yeah this works also on math
problems if there's like um
say um Parts there's parts of the math
problem which are completely irrelevant
they can actually for um a model uh and
it will try and remove
those so yeah this is um yeah just to to
show you really that uh chain of thought
and system two reasoning it's not just
for math problems there's like a lot of
things you a model can think about with
these intermediate uh tokens and fix a
lot of problems in all kinds of of uh
tasks it's trying to solve um this last
one I show it's the task with evaluation
so you've you're given a a question like
an instruction and two possible
responses you want the model to say
which of the two responses is better
which is a really important thing
uh for training as we show because you
could basically uh have a use that as a
reward model and it's also important for
evaluation as well but yeah you can also
do system to reasoning there so in this
paper Branch solve merge uh the way that
was done was again through prompting by
asking given uh that instruction to
first ask the language model to break
down its evaluation inter different
criteria such as relevance Clarity
accuracy originality and it would come
up with those criteria um specific to
the to the task that it's trying to
solve and then to um generate an
evaluation independently for each of
those um different uh branches so and
then merge them back together again and
it was shown that that could give better
evaluation results through the extra
thinking time
basically that the language model
has so yeah that was you know there's
other many other works as well during
that period but I just wanted to kind of
give a an overview of uh a few of them
to show there was a lot of prompting
approaches that showed that spending
time thinking could get you better
results
but what we really want to do is try and
train these models you know end to end
to be able to good at be good at
reasoning not like just prompting right
so I'd say the next wave after that is
and we're in it right now is improving
this reasoning through optimization and
so better reasoning via
self-improvement
um and to get there I'm going to start
with uh the self-rewarding language
models I was talking about right at the
the beginning of the
talk uh so this is a method where the
llm improves Itself by assigning rewards
to its own outputs and and uh optim
optimizing itself
so yeah where where the hope is that
this could lead to it becoming you know
smarter at each
iteration and
um yeah so the sort of um the research
question is can can that make it
superhuman um so the standard
reinforcement learning from Human
feedback which I mentioned earlier in
the talk uses humans in the loop first
to create the supervised fine-tuning
data So the instructions and the
responses and then to collect these
judgments so uh which of these two
responses is better A or
B now um yeah that's shown in this this
picture that I show before so there's
two spots where there's a human the uh
and the problem is language models are
getting better and better right so it's
just getting a really tricky job for
humans to
uh to be as good as we need for these
tasks humans need to read these
responses really carefully in order to
make uh
decisions so for example now that our
llms really good at writing code or uh I
know uh
sophisticated
um math outputs you know even getting
good at like I mean maybe not perfect
yet but getting good at legal or medical
outputs things like this the problem is
it's harder and harder for humans to be
good labelers for these tasks right you
might need some of the be best
mathematicians in human mathematicians
in the world right to label whether
these responses are correct or not right
and similar you need really good coders
um or even if you don't need them today
you'll certainly need them tomorrow
right and so the average sort of human
that you pick from the population they
they're just not going to be good enough
at these specialized tasks and be able
to annotate this data so this is what
motivates um trying to get the language
model to try and help itself uh and so
that's basically otherwise how can we
continue improving a model if it's
already you know fairly superum compared
to the average human that you could
pick so there's two observations that
can help us solve this observation one
is that we know language models can
continue improving if they're given good
judgments on response quality because
that's what was shown in reinforcement
learning from Human feedback or in
something like DPO as well right so if
you have good preferences of Chosen and
rejected pairs then you can improve the
model by training and pushing up the
probability of the chosens and uh down
the probability of rejected and the same
thing for for a reward model um with
reinforcement learning and observation
two is that we actually have Now
language models that can provide good
judgments on model generation so I was
showing you the branch solve merge
approach uh just earlier so that's an
approach for a language model basically
uh to give uh a judgment on on two
responses um as an instruction following
task so this is called llm as a judge
typically where uh you know for the
language model it's it's not any
different a task than all the other
instruction following tasks it has to do
like write some code or you know respond
to this particular question and in
particular this you know this question
we're asking is which of these two
responses better A or B so and you know
there's a a bunch of work showing llm as
a judge is actually uh a pretty good
method so how about combining these two
things together right so we replace the
human feedback feedback with the llm
feedback so the key idea then is to
train this so-called self-rewarding
language model this it's going to be its
own judge as it's training so it needs
to have this instruction following
capability uh for all the kinds of user
instructions we want but one of those
user instructions uh is actually the
evaluation task that we're interested in
so it looks like this here is an
instruction uh here is a model of
response and then the task is can you
assign a score say between zero and five
or there be other ways of doing that as
well but to this response and then based
on some some rubric and then you would
expect say a Chain of Thought reasoning
process and then a final Judgment of the
score of the response so if we have
these two things then we can make this
model train itself and be self-rewarding
so uh we also go through iterative
process of data creation and curation so
that we close this whole training Loop
where we train on this new data and then
uh the goal is the model is going to get
better in terms of both instruction
following and EV evaluation ability and
each cycle and we empirically showed
that that was possible so this was right
at the beginning of uh last
year so that was the picture that I was
showing right at the beginning of the of
the talk um so yeah we did these
experiments on on llama
270b um and we used open Assistant as a
sort of seed so that's seed instruction
data uh and it also has some seed
evaluation data um so the llm as a judge
prompt that we use looks like this so
that's um yeah asking it to to do Chain
of Thought and then score uh out of five
a particular
instruction and uh then we're going to
go through this training Loop so the
first part uh is it's going to generate
new tasks so we use something called
self- instruct to do that so basically
you start with your seed instructions
which are from humans and you use f shop
prompting with a few of those
instructions to ask the language model
to generate a new instruction okay and
then you can do this you know hundreds
or thousands of times to get whole new
set of tasks then for those tasks you
can generate responses so you'll
generate multiple candidate responses
for each uh prompt or task so in let's
say four in our case and then you
generate rewards with the L llm as a
judge prompt that I just showed to give
you those scores for each of the four
responses and from that you can generate
preference pairs so you take the highest
scoring of the four responses and that
would be the chosen for DPO and the
lowest scoring would be the rejected you
can carry on training your model now
with this DPO training and then repeat
the whole cycle now you have a better
model Mt plus1 you can go
back uh generate new prompts generate
new responses generate new rewards and
so on and we do this Loop like three
times in the experiments in that paper
and we're going to evaluate the
performance on two axes the ability to
follow instructions and its ability as a
reward model uh there's uh some
benchmarks called alpaca eval 2 an empty
bench at the time that we used and
another test set of
prompts and uh we use GPT for evaluation
and human evaluation to check how this
model performed through the three
iterations of self-rewarding and you can
see that they agree with each other uh
human and GPT 4 that we compare it to
doing supervised fine-tuning on each
iteration the model is getting better so
it's getting better than the uh sft
Baseline
um and yeah so that's a sort of power of
this self trining um and we can look at
the uh win rate on alpaca eval 2 and
this paper got quite a bit of attention
at the time because this win rate for um
such a sort of simple model was quite
good it started from this llama 70b and
it the win rate went up from 10% to 15%
to 20% in the three iterations which put
it almost on par of GPT a version of GPT
4 um and you know this was kind of just
done by um the first author is wer Juan
who's a PhD student NYU so there wasn't
like a big team building this project
but you know the algor them is Works
quite well um and uh yeah so you could
look at what it's actually improving at
and it does improve on all kinds of uh
skills but particularly more things like
Humanities extraction stem roleplay and
writing more than it improves let say
something like math code and reasoning
and the reason why that would be is
because the llm as a judge might not be
as good at evaluating math Cod and
reasoning and so it's harder for it to
improve on
those um this is a breakdown yeah of
these topics you can see that the gap on
the between the iterations is smaller
for things like math which is on the far
right um and then you can measure the
ability of this model
as an
evaluator and
um you could you know one way of
measuring that is by looking its
correlation with human judgments so the
pairwise accuracy we had a whole bunch
of metrics but the pairwise accuracy
metric would show its uh agreement with
humans on on whether a or b are the
right way round or the wrong way around
and you can see that does increase not
by a massive amount but it does increase
over the three iterations so it is
actually getting better at being a
reward model which I think is exciting
because if if the model's getting better
making judgments of what's right or
wrong then it's getting better at
rewarding
itself following instructions so there's
kind of a virtuous circle going on there
to some extent C it plateaus uh in
experiments but still this still gives
it the capacity to self-train and and
get to get better than the initial uh
human annotations that it had at the
beginning now uh as I said it didn't
improve as much on reasoning tasks so
the next thing we wanted to ask was how
can we make improve on those and uh yeah
so in uh April last year we did this
work called iterative reasoning
preference
optimization which I can see from the
picture it's um a similar pipeline but
now we're going to generate chain of
thoughts so in that in the in the
experiment I just showed you the there
were no chain of thoughts right it was
just kind of a system one language model
output the answers for instruction
following but in in in this version
we're going to generate chain of
thoughts and then answers and we're
going to compute rewards and otherwise
the the the pipeline is the same now the
rewards aren't going to be done by llm
as a judge because we don't trust the
llm on these uh these say these math
tasks uh as much I mean I think that's a
subject of research how you know can we
get them to improve by by trusting their
own judgments but in this work we just
said okay we've got a bunch of uh Math
training data where we know the right
answer so let's just use that as a
reward and uh this what's this is uh
being commonly called in the last uh
weeks is like uh a verifiable reward for
a math problem right so we what we're
going to do is we're going to do
generate the Chain of Thought uh and
then the final answer and then we're
going to extract the final answer from
the llm response so sort of remove the
Chain of Thought part just get the final
answer and then just do a match with the
answer that we know for the math problem
so you can do that with this kind of
prompt so uh where you give the LM The
Prompt your task is to answer the
question below give stepbystep reasoning
and when you're ready please use the
format Final Answer colon so then you
can just simply do this uh you know
heuristic extraction where you search
for final answer
colon grab the text afterwards that
should be your answer and now just do a
string match or some other fairly simple
match with the with the answer the known
gold
answer and um that's how you can build
your uh your DPO pairs um
and improve your model and then again
iterate round and that's the iteration
again is important because now we've got
a better model answering these math
problems we're going to generate new
chain of thoughts with a better model
compute the rewards and go around in a
loop um and uh we showed on math
problems like gsmk that that's working
really well um so yeah you can see these
improvements across iteration one to
four it's uh
gaining uh a little bit less than 10%
there and also improves on some
multi-choice problems on Arc Challenge
and on these harder math problems as
well
um and yeah we just showed that the uh
DPO training is really important you
can't just use supervised fine-tuning uh
with this training you really need the
negative examples to be pushed down
uh otherwise it doesn't work
um and yeah so in 2024 September or so
open AIS 01 came out of course the exact
method is UN unknown they didn't you
know publish a paper about it but they
did have uh well they didn't even show
the chain of thoughts either right from
the model there was a summary of the
chain of thoughts I think they still do
that uh but it was capable of answering
some quite Soph phisticated uh reasoning
math problems and everyone was wondering
how did they do it did they uh did they
use some kind of protest reward model
that was like evaluating in between
steps did they use MCTS or some really
sophisticated search mechanisms to train
with reinforcement learning or you know
uh a lot of ideas were posted on Twitter
of how they do this and then deep seek
R1 came out just uh this January and uh
Mark Chen from openai tweeted congrats
to deep seek on producing 01 level
reasoning model their research paper
demonstrates they've independently found
some of the core ideas that we did on
our way to 01 okay so then that means
assuming that open AI used the same
stuff as deep seek we have a deep seek
paper so we can look at what they did
and in you know in some respects it's
quite similar to the iterative reasoning
preference optimization that we did
earlier in 2024 that I just showed you
uh so they have a prompt which asks it
to think and then to put the answer in a
box you see this an answer here in the
prompt and then they they extract that
and uh then they use a rule based
verification of correctness of with
verifiable rewards and they you know
apply that in a loop generating chain of
thoughts checking just the correctness
of the answer and then rewarding this
correctness these a you know a different
um optimization technique they don't use
itative DPO they use uh
grpo but otherwise uh this recipe uh
looks kind of like that is just you know
done at much bigger scale so in the
experiments I showed you we just had
like one data set like
GSM uh so key here is start from a
really strong big model I think it's a
600 something parameter model right 671
billion parameter model um deep seek
three and then you know you have a large
amount of this reasoning data with
verifiable rewards and you train uh with
this RL generating chain of thoughts and
rewarding the ones that it gets right
and basically exploring the space of
chain of thoughts and you they observe
that the chain of thoughts get longer
over training as it finds sort of more
sophisticated um reasoning techniques
and then the final model does uh very
well on these code and math problems uh
similar to open ai's 01 model and this
actually uh was a big big news outside
of AI you can see um nvidia's uh
these articles here on Bloomberg Aid's
deep seat drop as Wall Street fixated
and with their stock plunging and stuff
like that so it was surprisingly big uh
Splash um and then yeah I have a couple
of examples here of the chain of
thoughts uh that it does the one on the
left is from their paper uh it's
generating this answer to this question
and then in the middle of it like the
chain of for says wait wait wait that's
an Ara moment I can flag here let's
re-evaluate this and it starts saying
some other stuff so they were just
showing how uh it learns to rethink and
uh you know fix its own mistakes and
that was all done just with this you
know this training that just rewarding
the final answer and it was doing the
rest itself and I I presently love the
Simplicity of it that we didn't have to
do you know really complicated things in
the middle it's just you know just
rewarding the end and uh
you can already get these impressive
results so the one on the right is kind
of a more funny one uh ask deep seek to
select a random number and it outputs
this large amount of Chain of Thought uh
where it sort of overthinks itself maybe
I should go with something like 7777 but
that's four sevens which might be too
obvious alternatively one two three two
sequential um what about if I close my
eyes and 42 Wait no that's from htis
guide and so on so it's pretty amusing
what it ends up doing uh but um yeah
almost a little human in the way though
but um but I don't think that's actually
the way we really want to Generate
random numbers obviously
um yeah
so from uh my own team's work um before
that came out so 2024 October we were uh
looking to
extend our Chain of Thought training
results from itative reasoning
preference optimization we show that
work quite well with math problems but
we want Chain of Thought reasoning for
all problems right um like even if
you're I don't know thinking about um
how to write a poem you might you know
do a whole bunch of thinking write some
drafts try and understand what what
you're going to write about before you
actually write here um just to pick an
example that's very different to a math
so we um try to follow the same recipe
so we have a a prompt uh a generic
prompt just to initialize the model and
we ask it to respond to whatever generic
query but do it in a comprehensive and
detailed Way by writing your internal
thoughts and then you must include this
draft response in its
evaluation and after you write your
final response uh have this special tag
so again that's so we can extract the
response out and separate it from the
thoughts um and this is the same trick
that we did before right and the same
trick that deep seek does um but here
we're going to do it not on math
problems but on all kinds of other
instruction following problems but now
we won't have a verifiable reward
anymore but we still have these um llm
as a judge right that we were using in
self-rewarding so we can use that on the
response to judge whether the uh
response is good but the difference
between this and the original
self-rewarding work is that we have the
Chain of Thought generation before it so
we tried this and um actually ended up
working quite well um it gave gains on
this alpaca eval and another Benchmark
called Arena hard it's actually third on
the alac alpaca
eval uh leaderboard I think at the time
and it was the best 8 billion parameter
model on Arena hard the I think one
interesting thing about the training so
again we're doing this iterative
training with DPO is that uh so this is
called
um um yeah thought preference
optimization TPO and we compare it to
the direct Baseline in this graph in the
bottom uh right which is basically no
chain of thought and you can see in the
first
iterations TPO actually makes the model
a lot
worse and that's because these language
models so we're using like
llama is it llama 38 bit 8 billion
they're already really well fine-tuned
to be good without the Chain of Thought
right so that kind of had a massive
advantage over trying to make it do the
Chain of Thought but after after we
train it on successful Chain of Thought
um outcomes using the llm as a judge or
the reward model then um you can see
that the Gap closes and then it starts
improving on iteration 3 and four now
it's better than the direct Baseline so
uh yeah so I think this is was really
promising because it showed you could do
this Chain of Thought training not just
for math problems or verify viable task
but for anything right
um and uh yeah so here's a a couple of
examples of things it does you know is
um so you can you know say for a query
write me a poem or what uh dog breed is
smallest it's going to do a whole bunch
of thinking like draft responses and
evaluation or various thought processes
before before it gives the
output yeah and then you know keep seek
R1 in their
paper not 100% sure if it's doing
something the same as what we're doing
there with TPO but there's there's a
Hint it is because it says here I
highlighted it for General data we
resort to reward models to capture human
preferences in complex and nuanced
scenarios uh so I think they're also
generating Chain of Thought and then
doing that but it wasn't wasn't like
fully spelled out in their so it wasn't
completely clear
um yeah uh and then there's other things
we can do so these as far to my
knowledge aren't actually yet in these
bigger models so these are more just
like uh research papers that hopefully
then get Scaled up to these bigger
models um the next work we did uh to try
to show that the language model so far
we've shown it's quite good at improving
its instruction and reasoning
ability but we also want to explicitly
improve its ability to evaluate itself
um because if we can do that then when
it's doing these judgments it's doing
these um reward model judgments it's
going to get better at everything right
it's going to get better at instruction
following as well so uh this work is
called meta rewarding language models
where it's going to try to improve its
own judgments by meta judging its
judgments so obviously a little bit meta
this this this work um but so yeah now
you can sort of see the language model
in three roles as an actor so following
instructions as a judge judging
responses to those instructions and as a
meta judge it's going to judge its own
judgments and I show you how you can do
that we call that llm as a meta judge so
there's a prompt for that so you'd have
uh a given instruction from the
user uh a
response from say a model and then
judgment a and judgment B which could
include the Chain of Thought and the
final
verdict and then you want the language
model to judge which of the judgments is
better A or
B now we have a particular algorithm
then for like basically taking all
different
judgments uh calculating the meta
judgments and then the ELO score amongst
them and but the reason to do that is to
create preference pairs amongst
judgments so now we can say okay this
judgment looks better than that judgment
because our meta judge uh you know tend
to say that and so we can construct
preference pairs again with
DPO of which judgments are better so now
we've got two types of reference pairs
the ones we had before which were like
response you know response chosen is
better than response rejected but now we
also have a judgment chosen is better
than judgment rejected and we train the
model with both types of data so this is
different to basically
self-rewarding uh language models that I
showed earlier only had the top part of
this picture right so it had didn't
really have an explicit mechanism to
improve its ability to
uh evaluate things and yeah so this work
I think it's exciting
because it helps uh we actually get
better um win rates on um say alpaca
eval uh with that and
um yeah uh this plot you can see
again um we see the improvement over
iteration
but it's above the um the performance of
the self-rewarding model that doesn't
have this meta judge training and even
the yeah the the um self-rewarding model
tends to Plateau a bit here on iteration
4 whereas it's still going up um for The
Meta rewarding
model so I think that's pretty exciting
and um yeah I've got one more
thing to talk about which is um
how to improve the chain of thoughts for
uh judgments for evaluation so that's
another recent work actually only out
last last week um so this is called uh
this works called thinking llm as a
judge um and uh the goal is to generate
these long chain of thoughts similar to
o1 R1 but for the task of judgment of
responses again so that we have good
rewards for training our models so
here's an example from the model we
trained of what it can do uh outputs
this evaluation plan of how it's going
to evaluate and then sort of executes on
the plan gives this final verdict yeah
so we have sort of a training mechanism
for
that and the trick here is um you can
look at the
um the evaluation task actually is a
verifiable task if you know which of two
responses is better so let's say you've
got an instruction you've got response a
and response B if you know in advance
that a is better or B is better then
that's like a verifiable task right like
the math tasks we can we can compute the
reward directly right we don't need a
say a language model llm as a judge um
to to agree right with um with our
output so the trick in this work the
first trick is to generate synthetic uh
evaluation data so that we have a
verifiable task so we know which one's
better and once we have that verifiable
task we can essentially do something a
bit like the itive reasoning preference
optimization IPO because we can compute
the rewards directly right and build
these preference pairs uh to improve the
chain of thoughts for
evaluation um there's a couple of extra
details here where in this particular
case we actually asked it to do a plan
first and then execute on the plan which
is this uh to is the left hand part of
this
figure
um so how do we create this verifiable
data so this comes from uh previous
paper we did called selft
evaluators uh what we're going to do is
we um given a prompt X we generate a
good response with a language model or
at least we think it's a good response
let's say it's a reasonable response and
then we generate a similar PR X
Prime uh which is similar but different
to X and then we also use the llm same
llm to generate a good response to X
Prime we call that y Prime and now the
hope is uh that of course because X
Prime is different to X um y Prime won't
be as good a response to X right so
that's the thing that basically y should
be preferred over y Prime for input X so
this now becomes our verifiable task
that we're going to use for training so
so the only question there
that was a bit of an unknown was how to
how do you make this similar but
different prompt and of course we use
llm to do that as well right so we say
please generate a modified instruction
that's highly relevant but not
semantically identical to the
instruction above and then this is what
gives us the uh the similar instruction
which we can then generate the the lower
quality response for the original
instruction
from um and yeah that's rough the higher
level picture of this work uh there's
some uh ablation studies here where we
showed that um these plans are superior
to not thinking at all so no Chain of
Thought but in general it's good to have
the the plants as unconstrained as
possible like if you encourage them to
be for example lists of criteria or
verif verification questions which some
other works have used with prompting
then then the results get worse and I
think that's kind of in line with the o1
R1 style results as well where basically
you don't want to constrain too much the
Chain of Thought thinking processes of
these language models but you want to
kind of you know train and find out what
what it's going going to be good at
um and then yeah after we train this
model using llama uh 3.1 or 3.3 70b as a
base
where uh it gets uh very good results
it's actually state-of-the-art on uh
this Benchmark called reward bench which
evaluates reward models uh for llm as a
judge like generative models and it's
also quite good on some harder
evaluation tasks or some newer
benchmarks that just came out like RM
bench and follow bench
EV
um and yeah that's really all the all
the things I'm going to talk about I
think I talked about enough already
right uh so just a little bit of a
summary of these these recent works from
the last
year um self-rewarding models uh they
they're models that can train themselves
to get better and the hope is that could
be a path to superhuman AI as the model
improves
itself um we've seen how verifiable
rewards can help to train Chain of
Thought for better reasoning uh so I
showed you this iterative reasoning
preference optimization technique but
deep seek and o1 have you know related
techniques uh basically all using these
verifiable rewards on the on the output
and then letting the Chain of Thought
kind of uh don't you know penalize it
just find ones that work well during
during your um your training
cycle and then you can also use these
verifiable rewards to improve the
evaluation ability of the model so
that's the thinking llm as a judge that
I just showed and then of course these
if we have these better judges with this
Chain of
Thought the whole thing can go in a
cycle right we can help those we can use
those to help train to think on
nonverifiable tasks because we can use
this thinking llm as a judge to to train
those models and we call that thinking
llms which I showed earlier as well and
then finally uh you can use this met
rewarding concept that judge their own
judgments is another way of improving
their evaluation ability so I've s shown
you a few sort of separate papers uh but
you know kind of the goal of the bigger
model releas is try and put some of
these ideas together so uh yeah some of
those more recent things like meta
rewarding and thinking llms kind of need
to go together with the earlier uh ideas
all in in one system and we'll see see
how far we can push that and of course
still looking for new ideas right and
they're they're going to be coming in
the coming days weeks months and years
I'm sure so
um yeah uh of course there's you know
lots of other directions uh and you know
just to throw one out there is all the
reasoning I've been talking about was um
with chain of thoughts that were text
right it's generating text from the
language model now you don't have to do
that right you could like the
transformer itself does reasoning
by uh all these
multiplications you know inside the
neuronet it's all manipulating vectors
right in the hidden states of the
network and so why does this system to
reasoning have to be tokens so maybe
that could also be these continuous
vectors as well so we explored that in a
recent paper um method called
coconut where we replace the Chain of
Thought of like outputting tokens with
outputting vectors
instead and um we showed that has some
promise actually it could say at least
match the performance on some tasks and
even out perform classical Chain of
Thought on some more difficult search
tasks um uh but these are all quite
small scale tasks so remains to be seen
sort of how far people can push that
direction I think there's some reasons
to want to have the Chain of Thought in
human language natural language I think
it's a nice thing for safety and
interpretability um but you know uh the
as I said the neural network itself
isn't interpretable in that way right
the internals of the Transformer so
that's something we have to work out I
think
um and I got another slide about what
else comes next I think there's so much
more exciting research to be done uh so
ilas
ITA uh in his seek to seek uh paper test
of time award that was this last np's uh
talk he uh
presented some things this is a a
picture of what he was saying what comes
next was mentioning agents uh synthetic
data inference time compute uh reasoning
understanding and being self-aware which
all makes sense and I think these are
all things that you know people are
working on today apart well maybe the
self-aware ones is a little more little
more fuzzy but the other ones at least
and yeah I would say that uh I would
just add some more detail there I think
self-improving um self evaluation is
really important because that b neck's
performance um so using more of this
inference time compute for evaluation is
only going to help self-improve the
model and I think that's sort of related
to this
self-aware uh comment that he makes here
that a selw you know model might be more
able to understand what it it knows and
what it doesn't know right which is kind
of
evaluation and then learning from
interaction I think learning how to
Reason by actually interacting with
people in the world internet or itself
uh are important things and this that's
related to the agent point and the
synthetic data point he makes there and
then of course not it's not just about
improving the system to reasoning I
think improve if we can improve system
one reasoning uh so like the transformer
architecture itself then that's great
too so maybe there's a better
attention uh model some sort of um or
maybe something new a new a neuron
Network layer we you know haven't come
up with yet that could change like the
scaling laws
um uh and and the performance of these
models and that's great too so um yeah
Lenny to do and it's going to be
exciting to see what happens um thank
you